
<exercise>
<statement><p>How many positive integers not exceeding 2019 are multiples of 3 or 4 but not 5? You would count the numbers 3, 12, and 16, but not 15 or 20.</p></statement>
<solution><p>The number of integers that are multiples of 3 or 4, but inclusion-exclusion is <m>\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{3}\right\rfloor +\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{4}\right\rfloor
-\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{12}\right\rfloor =673+504-168=1009</m>. But we need to remove the multiples of 5 from this total. The multiples of
5 are <m>\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{15}\right\rfloor +\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{20}\right\rfloor -\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{60}\right\rfloor =134+100-33=201</m>. The final answer is then <m>1009-201=808</m>.
</p></solution></exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>For a positive constant <m>k</m>, consider the region <m>\mathcal{R}</m> bounded by the line<m>y = k x</m> and the parabola <m>y = x^2</m>. There is only
one choice of <m>k</m> such that the solids obtained by revolving <m>\mathcal{R}</m> about the <m>x</m>-axis and the <m>y</m>-axis have the same
volume. Find the value of this special choice of <m>k</m>.</p></statement>
<solution><p>The volume of revolution around the <m>x</m> axis is 
<me>\int_0^k \pi \left((k x)^2-x^4\right) \, dx=\frac{2\pi }{15}k^5</me>.
Around the <m>y</m> axis we have (using shells) 
<me>\int _0^k2\pi  x\left(k x-x^2\right)dx=\frac{\pi }{6}k^4</me>.
Therefore the special <m>k</m> is <m>\frac{5}{4}</m>.
</p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>A rectangle with sides <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, <m>a<b,</m> is rotated about its center, as shown in the figure, so that the two rectangles share two vertices.
 What is the area of the parallelogram that makes up the intersection of the two rectangles?</p></statement>
<solution><p>
Let <m>c</m> be the length of the horizontal sides of the parallelogram, so the area we are looking for is <m>a c</m>. The triangles that are outside
the parallelogram are right triangles with hypotenuse <m>c</m>, and sides <m>b-c</m> and <m>a</m>.  
<me>(b-c)^2+a^2= c^2 \Rightarrow \textrm{   }c=\frac{a^2+ b^2}{2b }\textrm{  }\Rightarrow \textrm{  Area } =\frac{a}{2b} \left(a^2+ b^2\right)</me>
</p></solution></exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>Show that every set of <m>n</m> integers has a nonempty subset such that the sum of its elements is divisible by <m>n</m>.</p></statement>
<solution><p>
Let <m>a_1, a_2, \dots , a_n</m> be the integers and let <m>s_1, s_2, \dots , s_n</m> be the partial sums, <m>s_k=\sum _{i=1}^k
a_i</m>.  If one of the sums is divisible by <m>n</m> then we are done, so assume none are multiples of <m>n</m>.  By the pigeonhole principle,
there must be two partial sums that have the same residue mod <m>n</m>.  Let <m>l \lt m </m> be such that 
	<me>s_l\equiv s_m(mod n) \Rightarrow s_m-s_l= \sum _{k=l+1}^m a_k=n q</me> for some integer <m>q</m>.  Therefore the set we are looking for is <m>\left\{a_{l+1}, \ldots, a_m\right\}</m>.
</p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>Suppose two teams play a series of games in which the probability that either wins any of the games is <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>.  If they play a best
of seven series, where the winner is the first to win four games, what is the probability that the series lasts seven games?</p></statement>
<solution><p>
In order for the series to go seven games, the teams must split the first six games. Imagine that they play out six games no matter what happens.
There are <m>2^6</m> equally likely outcomes and in <m>\binom{6}{3}=20</m> of the cases the teams split. Therefore, the probability of a seven games
series <m>\frac{20}{2^6}= \frac{5}{16}</m>.</p></solution>
</exercise>
