<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- MBX -->
<chapter xml:id="c-prerequisites">
<title>Format for a Problem Solving Class</title>
<introduction><p>This chapter contains note on the way I teach a problem solving class.  I'm sure that there are plenty of variations that work at least as well, and I hope this will provide the reader with ideas for their own system.</p>
</introduction>
<section><title>Before the first class</title>
<p>Students in my class are required to compete in the Putnam but in a typical year there are an equal number of students who are not in class who are interested in the Putnam.  Since it's never to early to start preparing, I post warm-up problems on Piazza.com.   As students register for the class, many in the spring, I add them to the Piazza list, which also includes the non-registered students.  I post problems that are not quite up to the difficulty of Putnam problems - in fact many are way easier.  However, this lets students rediscover some basic concepts.  Solutions are available to students even if they register late, and so these problems serve as a starting point to the course.</p>
</section>
<section><title>The first class</title>
<p>In the first class, we review two basic proof tools, mathematical induction and the pigeonhole principle. I suggest starting the class by reviewing these two topics through examples.  I try to be as careful as possible in writting the solutions in a logically coherent form, setting the tone for what I will expect to see from students.   The choice of Fermat's Little Theorem for the induction proof also anticipates a later class in which we do Number Theory.  I don't dwell on these examples any longer than necessary, shooting for a total time of around 30 minutes.</p>
<p>I normally divide the class into groups of 2, 3 or 4 to work on problems.  Exactly how this is done depends on class size, and other factors.   The first problem is a warm-up in that I expect several students to have seen it already.  I instruct the class to work  on this one first with the expectation that most groups will complete it within ten minutes.   I circulate among the groups to help anyone who is struggling with the first problem.   I assign the rest of the problems to different groups.  I encourage the groups to put solutions on the board when they are ready.  When a few problems have been written out, we take a break from solving to review the solutions. Groups that have completed a problem are assigned a new one and we continue until the period is almost over.  Normally a few problems are left unsolved and they are assigned for homework.</p>
</section>
<section><title>Subsequent classes</title>
<p>In the second class, we focus on some counting techniques and indirect proofs.  Again, we spend only a short time reviewing these concepts after having discussed some of the problems from week 1.  I leave plenty of time to work on these new problems. Students should be aware that not every solution to problems that are posed in a given week use the technique that is highlighted in that week. </p>
</section>
<section><title>Some <q>Prerequisite</q> Topics</title>
<p>With the assumption that we have to start somewhere, I give students a list, certainly not complete, of topics that expect students to have a good grasp of to participate in the class.</p>
<list><title>Prerequisites</title>
<ul>
<li><p>Properties of the complex numbers</p></li>
<li><p>Circular function definition of the trig functions.</p></li>
<li><p>Expected Value of a random variable</p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
<li><p></p></li>
</ul>
</list>
</section>
</chapter>
