<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- MBX -->
<chapter xml:id="c-prerequisites">
<title>Format for a Problem Solving Class</title>
<introduction><p>This chapter contains note on the way I teach a problem solving class.  I'm sure that there are plenty of variations that work at least as well, and I hope this will provide the reader with ideas for their own system.</p>
</introduction>
<section><title>Before the first class</title>
<p>Piazza</p>
</section>
<section><title>The first class</title>
<p>In the first class, we review two basic proof tools, mathematical induction and the pigeonhole principle. I suggest starting the class by reviewing these two topics through examples.  I try to be as careful as possible to write the solutions in a logically coherent form, setting the tone for what I will expect to see from students.   The choice of Fermat's Little Theorem for the induction proof also anticipates the Class 3 in which we do Number Theory.  I don't dwell on these examples any longer than necessary, shooting for a total time of around 30 minutes.</p>
<p>I normally divide the class into groups of 2, 3 or 4 to work on problems.  Exactly how this is done depends on class size, and other factors.  See Appendix 1 for details.   The first problem is a warm-up in that I expect several students to have seen it already.  I instruct the class to work  on this one first with the expectation that most groups will complete it within ten minutes.   I circulate among the groups to help anyone who is struggling with the first problem.   I assign the rest of the problems to different groups.  I encourage the groups to put solutions on the board when they are ready.  When a few problems have been written out, we take a break from solving to review the solutions. Groups that have completed a problem are assigned a new one and we continue until the period is almost over.</p>
</section>
<section><title>Subsequent classes</title>
<p>In the second class, we focus on some counting techniques and indirect proofs.  Again, we spend only a short time reviewing these concepts after having discussed some of the problems from week 1.  Leave plenty of time to work on these new problems. Students should be aware that not every solution to problems that are posed in a given week use the technique that is highlighted in that week. </p>
</section>
<section><title>Complex Numbers</title>
<p>Properties of the complex numbers</p>
<p>Circular function definition of the trig functions.</p>
<p>Expected Value of a random variable</p>
</section>
</chapter>
