<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- MBX -->
<chapter xml:id="c-counting">
<title>Counting and Indirect Proofs</title>
<!-- 
<introduction><p>___ </p>
</introduction>
 -->
<section><title>Counting Two Ways</title>
<p>Most students are familiar with formula for a binomial coefficient,<m>\binom{n}{k}</m>. Here, we will derive the formula by two-way counting.</p>
<example xml:id="ex-binomial-coeff-formula">
<idx>Binomial Coefficient Formula, Derivation</idx>
<statement>
<p>The binomial coefficient <m>\binom{n}{k}</m> represents the  the number of <m>k</m> element subsets of an <m>n</m> element set , <m>0\leq k\leq n</m>.</p>
<p>We will count the number of ways to permute <m>k</m>  objects from a set of <m>n</m> elements two ways.  First, we can first choose one of the <m>k</m> element subsets of of the set, and second, choose one of the <m>k!</m>  permutations of those elements. By the rule of products, we can do this <m> \binom{n}{k} \cdot k!</m>.  A second approach is to select the the elements from our set to go into positions 1 through <m>k</m> in the permutation immediately.  The number of ways of doing this is <m>n \cdot (n-1)\cdot \cdots \cdot (n-(k-1))</m>.   The two expressions count the same number and so they are equal. We equate them and then solve for the value of the  binomial coefficient:  <m>\binom{n}{k} =\frac{n!}{k! \cdot (n-k)!}</m>.</p>
</statement>
</example>
</section>  

<section><title>Indirect Proofs</title>
<example><title>No Least Positive Real Number</title>
<p>Prove that there is no least positive real number.</p>
<p>Assume that there is a least positive real number, which we'll call <m>L</m>.  Certainly, we can assume that <m>L \lt 1</m> since we know of many positive real number that statisfy this inequality.  If we multiply the inequality by <m>L</m>, we find that <m>L^2 \lt L</m>.  Since <m>L^2</m> is a positive real number we have a contradiction that <m>L</m> is least.  Hence no such least number can exist.</p>
</example>
<example><title>The Harmonic Series</title><idx>Harmonic Series</idx>
<p>Students often struggle with the idea that although the terms of the harmonic series, <m>\sum_{n=1}^{\infty} \frac{1}{n}</m>, converge to zero, the series itself diverges. Encountering this fact in a calculus class in which proof may not be emphasized is often the problem.  Many of the dozens of proofs that the harmonic series diverges are indirect.  Here is one such example.</p>
<p>Assume the series converges and its limit is <m>H</m>.
	<me>\begin{split}
		H &amp;= 1 + \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{3} + \frac{1}{4} +\cdots + \frac{1}{2k-1} + \frac{1}{2k} + \cdots\\
		&amp; \gt  \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{4} +\cdots + \frac{1}{2k} + \frac{1}{2k} + \cdots\\
		&amp; = 1 + \frac{1}{2} +  +\cdots + \frac{1}{k}  + \cdots\\
		&amp; = H
		  \end{split}
	</me> 
The contradiction we arrive at, <m>H \gt H</m>, implies that the series does indeed diverge.
</p>
</example>

</section>  

<exercises><title>Problems</title>

<exercise number="1">
<statement>
<p>Let <m>S</m> be a set of real numbers which is closed under multiplication (that is, if <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are in <m>S</m>, then so is <m>a b</m>). Let <m>T</m> and <m>U</m> be disjoint subsets of <m>S</m> whose union is <m>S</m>. Given that the product of any three (not necessarily distinct) elements of <m>T</m> is in <m>T</m> and that the product of any three elements of <m>U</m> is in <m>U</m>, show that at least one of the two subsets <m>T</m>, <m>U</m> is closed under multiplication.</p>
</statement>
<solution><p>Assume neither <m>T</m> nor <m>U</m> is closed.  Then there exist <m>t_1, t_2\in T</m> and <m>u_1, u_2 \in U</m> such that <m>t_1\cdot t_2 \in U</m> and <m>u_1 \cdot u_2 \in T</m>.  We can observe that <m>(t_1\cdot t_2)\cdot(u_1 \cdot u_2)</m> is a product of either three elements of <m>T</m>, or a product of three elements of <m>U</m>, meaning that it would be in the intersection, which is a contradiction.  Therefore one of the sets is closed.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise number="2">
<statement>
<p>Let's say I have a group of <m>n+1</m> people who want to see a show. Assume they all have different ages.  I have three tickets into the theatre: a backstage pass and two regular (but distinguishable)
tickets. I have to give out the tickets according to the following two rules:
<ol>
<li>The backstage pass must go to the oldest person who gets a ticket. </li>
<li>The person who gets the backstage pass can't get either of the other two tickets, but the two normal tickets can both go to the same person.</li>
</ol>
How many ways can I give away the tickets? There are two ways to count. Find both and equate them.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>You get two different results depending on whether you select who will be oldest first, or you decide what three people will get tickets first.</p>
</hint>
</exercise>

<exercise number="3">
<statement>
<p> Consider paths such as the one in the grid below that start at the bottom left, <m>(0,0),</m> and reach the top right, <m>(10,10)</m>.  These paths can only go up and to the right.  How many paths are there in all? How many of those paths pass through the point <m>(4,6)</m>?  Generalize both of your results.</p>
            <figure xml:id="lattice_path">
                <caption>A Lattice Path
                </caption>
                <image source="images/lattice_path.png" width="60%">
                    <description>A lattice path from (0,0) to (10,10).</description>
                </image>
            </figure>
 

</statement>
<hint><p>Think of each path as a sequence of instructions to go right (R) and up (U).</p></hint>
<answer><p>There are <m>\binom{m+n}{m}</m> paths</p></answer>
<solution><p>Each path can be described as a sequence or R's and U's with exactly ten of each.   The ten positions in which R's could be placed can be selected from the twenty positions in the sequence <m>\binom{20}{10}</m> ways.  We can generalize this logic and see that there are <m>\binom{m+n}{m}</m> paths from <m>(0,0)</m> to <m>(m,n)</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>

<exercise number="4">
<statement>
<p>Prove that if <m>n\geq 1</m>, then <m>\sum _{k=0}^n \binom{n}{k}^2=\binom{2 n}{n}</m></p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Consider the lattice paths from <m>(0,0)</m> to <m>(n,n)</m> passing through any point on the diagonal <m>i + j = n</m>.</p></hint>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise number="5">
<statement>
<p>Prove that the number of odd coefficients in each row of Pascal's triangle is a power of 2.</p>

</statement>
<solution><p></p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise number="6">
<statement>
<p>Every point of three-dimensional space is colored red, green, or blue. Prove that one of the colors attains all distances, meaning that any positive real number represents the distance between two points of this color.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>If false, there are <q>non-attainable</q> distances for each color.  Call them <m>r</m>, <m>g</m> and <m>b</m>, with  <m> r \leq g \leq b</m>.</p>
</hint>
</exercise>


<exercise number="7">
<statement>
<p> How many positive integers <m>n</m> are there such that <m>n</m> is a divisor of at least one the numbers <m>10^{40}</m> and <m>20^{30}</m>?</p>
</statement>
<solution><p>We will use the general rule that if an integer's prime factorization is 
<m>p_1^{\alpha_1}\cdot p_2^{\alpha_2}\cdot \cdots \cdot p_m^{\alpha_m}</m>, then it has 
<m>(\alpha_1 + 1)\cdot (\alpha_2 + 1)\cdot \cdots \cdot (\alpha_m + 1)</m> divisors.</p>
<p>By inclusion-exclusion, the number divisors of either number is the sum of the numbers of divisors of each number minus the number of common divisors.  The numbers that divide both are divisors of <m>2^{40}\cdot 5^{30}</m>.  Therefore, the answer is 
<me>41 \cdot 41 + 61 \cdot 31 - 41\cdot 31 = 2301.</me></p>
</solution>
</exercise>


<exercise number="8">
<statement>
<p>Prove that a list can be made of all the subsets of a finite set such that
<ul>
<li>the empty set is the first set;</li>
<li>each subset occurs once;</li>
<li>each subset is obtained from the preceding by adding or deleting an element.</li>
<li>the first subset obtained from the last by adding or deleting an element.</li>
</ul></p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>How many positive integers not exceeding 2019 are multiples of 3 or 4 but not 5? You would count the numbers 3, 12, and 16, but not 15 or 20.</p></statement>
<solution><p>The number of integers that are multiples of 3 or 4, but inclusion-exclusion is <m>\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{3}\right\rfloor +\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{4}\right\rfloor
-\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{12}\right\rfloor =673+504-168=1009</m>. But we need to remove the multiples of 5 from this total. The multiples of
5 are <m>\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{15}\right\rfloor +\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{20}\right\rfloor -\left\lfloor \frac{2019}{60}\right\rfloor =134+100-33=201</m>. The final answer is then <m>1009-201=808</m>.
</p></solution></exercise>

</exercises>
</chapter> 