<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- MBX -->

<chapter xml:id="c-geometry">
<title>Geometry</title>
<introduction>
<p>There are three basic approaches to geometric problems:
<ol marker="(1)">
<li><p>Axiomatic approach, where everything is deduced from basic facts, such as congruence tests for triangles (SAS, ASA, and SSS), similarity of triangles,
angles in the circle theorem, etc. These problems are good practice, but you are unlikely to see them on the Putnam exam.</p></li>
<li><p> Method of coordinates. Points on the plane are interpreted as coordinates <m>(x,y) \in \mathbb{R}^2</m>, or vectors, or complex numbers. Calculations
can often be simplified by using basic linear algebra (scalar products, etc.) and knowing geometric interpretations of various algebraic operations
(e.g. multiplication of complex numbers). Alternatively, a lot of things can be computed using trig functions.</p></li>
<li><p> Symmetries and transformations. This is a more dynamic approach, where you apply and compose rotations, symmetries, etc.</p></li>
</ol>
Often, problems are only formulated using geometric language but the solution uses some counting trick, or combinatorics, etc.</p>
</introduction>

<section xml:id="geomentry-examples">
<title>Examples</title>
<p>This is a useful <q>lemma</q> that lets you convert a statement about the angle between two line sgements to a statement about distances between endpoints.</p>
<lemma xml:id="lemma-geometry-1">
<statement><p>Two line segment on the plane <m>AB</m> and <m>CD</m> are perpendicular if and only if <m>\lvert AC \rvert^2 +  \lvert BD \rvert^2 = \lvert AD \rvert^2 + \lvert BC \rvert^2</m></p></statement>
<proof>
<case><title>(<m>\Rightarrow</m>)</title> <p>Assuming the two segments are perpendicular, we locate the point of intersection, <m>M</m>, of the two lines they determine, as in <xref ref="fig-sageplot-2segments-perp" text="type-global" />.  In the figure, we assume that <m>M</m> does not lie on either segment, but the equations below still apply in other cases. The right angle at <m>M</m> determines four right triangles and thus
	<me>
	\begin{split}
		\lvert AC\rvert^2 = \lvert MA\rvert^2 +\lvert  MC\rvert^2 
					\qquad &amp;\lvert AD\rvert^2 =\lvert  MA\rvert^2 + \lvert MD\rvert^2 \\
		\lvert BD\rvert^2 = \lvert MB\rvert^2 +\lvert MD\rvert^2 
					\qquad &amp;\lvert BC\rvert^2 = \lvert MB\rvert^2 + \lvert MC\rvert^2
		\end{split}
	</me></p>
<p>If we add the equations on the right and also the two on the left, we get the desired conclusion.</p>
</case>
<case><title>(<m>\Leftarrow</m>)</title><p>Again, let <m>M</m> be the point of intersection of the two extended segments.  In  <xref ref="fig-sageplot-2segments-notperp" text="type-global" /> we depict the case where <m>M</m> lies on both segments.  We assume the angle between the segments is not <m>\pi/2</m> and so we assume that <m>\angle AMC \gt \pi/2</m>.  Thus, the left sides of the equations above that are on the left are now greater than the right sides, while the left sides of the equations on the right are less than the right sides.  Therefore, <m>\lvert AC \rvert^2 +  \lvert BD \rvert^2 \gt \lvert AD \rvert^2 + \lvert BC \rvert^2</m>.</p>
<p>Finally, how can this special case be used to prove the case when <m>M</m> is does not lie on both segments?</p>
</case>

<sidebyside>
<figure xml:id="fig-sageplot-2segments-perp">
  <caption>Two perpendicular segments</caption>
  <image source="images/sageplot-2segments-perp.png" width="50%">
    <description>Figure illustrating the lemma, perpendicular case</description>
<!-- 
<sageplot>
fig=Graphics()
for p in [point((-1,5),size=30),point((1,1),size=30),point((4,1),size=30),point((6,2),size=30),point((8/5,-1/5),size=30,color="red")]:
    fig+=p
fig+=text("B",(-0.75,5))
fig+=text("A",(1.25,1))
fig+=text("D",(5.75,1.75))
fig+=text("C",(3.75,1))
fig+=text("M",(1.75,-1/3))
fig+=line([(-1,5),(1,1)])
fig+=line([(4,1),(6,2)])
fig+=line([(-1,5),(1,1)])
fig+=line([(8/5,-1/5),(1,1)],color="red",linestyle="-.")
fig+=line([(8/5,-1/5),(4,1)],color="red",linestyle="-.")
fig+=line([(1,1),(6,2)],color="purple")
fig+=line([(1,1),(4,1)],color="purple")
fig+=line([(-1,5),(6,2)],color="purple")
fig+=line([(-1,5),(4,1)],color="purple")
fig.show(axes=False)
</sageplot>
 -->
  </image>
</figure>  
<figure xml:id="fig-sageplot-2segments-notperp">
  <caption>Two segments that are not perpendicular</caption>
  <image source="images/sageplot-2segments-notperp.png" width="50%">
    <description>Figure illustrating the lemma, non-perpendicular case</description>
<!-- 
<sageplot>
A=(1,1)
B=(-1,5)
C=(-1,2)
D=(6,2)
M=(1/2,2)
fig=Graphics()
for p in [point(B,size=30),point(A,size=30),point(C,size=30),point(D,size=30),point(M,size=30,color="red")]:
    fig+=p
fig+=text("B",(-0.75,5))
fig+=text("A",(1.05,1.2))
fig+=text("D",(5.75,1.75))
fig+=text("C",(-0.75,2.2))
fig+=text("M",(0.75,2.15))
fig+=line([B,A])
fig+=line([C,D])
fig+=line([B,A])
fig+=line([A,D],color="purple")
fig+=line([A,C],color="purple")
fig+=line([B,D],color="purple")
fig+=line([B,C],color="purple")
fig.show(axes=False)
</sageplot>
 -->
</image>
</figure>
</sidebyside>
</proof>
</lemma>

</section>  


<exercises>
<title>Exercises</title>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Prove that a central angle subtended by a given circular arc is twice the angle of an inscribed angle for the same arc.
</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Inscribe a rectangle of base <m>b</m> and height <m>h</m> and an isosceles triangle of base <m>b</m> in a circle of radius one as shown in <xref ref="fig-geometry2" text="type-global" />. For what value of <m>h</m> do the rectangle and triangle have the same area? </p>
             <figure xml:id="fig-geometry2">
                <caption>When do the rectangle and triangle have the same area?
                </caption>
                <image source="images/fig-geometry2.png" width="60%">
                    <description>Inscribe a rectangle of base b and height h in a circle of radius one. Further inscribe an isosceles triangle of base b between the b-side of the rectangle and the minor arc of the circle that it determines.</description>
                </image>
            </figure>

</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>What convex quadrilaterals can be inscribed into a circle? There is a name for these quadrilaterals, but your answer should describe them, not
just name them</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>A rectangle with sides <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, <m>a \lt b</m> is rotated about its center, as shown in <xref ref="rotated-rectangle" text="type-global" />, so that the two rectangles share two vertices.
 What is the area of the parallelogram that makes up the intersection of the two rectangles?</p>
             <figure xml:id="rotated-rectangle">
                <caption>What is the area of the intersection?
                </caption>
                <image source="images/rotated-rectangle.png" width="60%">
                    <description>Figure for exercise</description>
                </image>
            </figure>
</statement>
<solution><p>
Let <m>c</m> be the length of the horizontal sides of the parallelogram, so the area we are looking for is <m>a c</m>. The triangles that are outside
the parallelogram are right triangles with hypotenuse <m>c</m>, and sides <m>b-c</m> and <m>a</m>.  
<me>(b-c)^2+a^2= c^2 \Rightarrow \textrm{   }c=\frac{a^2+ b^2}{2b }\textrm{  }\Rightarrow \textrm{  Area } =\frac{a}{2b} \left(a^2+ b^2\right)</me>
</p></solution></exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Prove that if the lengths of the sides of a triangle form an arithmetic progression, then the radius of the inscribed circle is one third of one
of the heights of the triangle.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Try two-way counting.</p></hint>
<solution><p>Assume the sides of the triangle are <m>b-d</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>b+d</m>; and that the altitude to the side of length <m>b</m> is <m>h</m>. Let <m>r</m> be the radius of the inscribed circle.  If we connect the center of the inscribed circle to the vertices of the triangle, the area of the triangle is the sum of areas of three triangles with height <m>r</m> the sides of the triangles as bases.  Therefore,
<me> \frac{1}{2} b \cdot h = \frac{1}{2} r(b-d)+ \frac{1}{2} r\cdot b+ \frac{1}{2} r(b+d) = \frac{1}{2}r(3\cdot b) = \frac{1}{2}b(3\cdot r)</me>
Therefore, <m>r=\frac{1}{3}\cdot b</m></p></solution>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>A piece of paper is in the shape of a rectangle <m>ABCD</m> with <m>AB=CD=3</m> and <m>AD=BC=5</m>.
The paper is folded so that <m>A</m> and <m>C</m> coincide. Find the length of the crease.  Generalize your result.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>The line connecting <m>A</m> and <m>C</m> is perpendicular to the fold.</p></hint>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>On the hyperbola <m>x y = 1</m> consider four points whose <m>x</m>-coordinates are <m>x_1</m>, <m>x_2</m>, <m>x_3</m>, and <m>x_4</m>. Show that if these points lie on a circle, then <m>x_1 \cdot  x_{2} \cdot x_{3}\cdot x_4 = 1</m>.</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Let <m>ABC</m> be a triangle and let the angle bisector of <m>\angle A</m> intersect the side <m>BC</m> at a point <m>D</m>. Show that <m>\frac{A B}{A C} = \frac{B D}{C D}</m>.</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>A trapezoid and a triangle are inscribed a circle. One side of the trapezoid is a diameter of the circle and the sides of the  triangle are parallel to sides of the trapezoid, as shown in <xref ref="fig_trap_tri" text="type-global" />. Prove that the trapezoid and triangle have the same area.
</p>
             <figure xml:id="fig_trap_tri">
                <caption>Do the trapezoid and triangle have equal areas?
                </caption>
                <image source="images/fig_trap_tri.png" width="60%">
                    <description>Figure described by the exercise</description>
                </image>
            </figure>

</statement>
<hint><p>Use coordinates with the circle at the origin and the diameter on the <m>x</m>-axis.  You can assume that the radius of the circle is <m>1</m>.</p></hint>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Let <m>f</m> be a real-valued function on the plane such that for every square <m>ABCD</m> in the plane, <m>f(A) + f(B) + f(C) + f(D) = 0</m>. Does it follow that <m>f(P) = 0</m> for all points <m>P</m> in the plane?</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Start with a square and divide it into four squares.</p></hint>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Given nine lattice points in <m>\mathbb{R}^3</m> prove that there exist two of them with the property that the midpoint of the segment between them is a lattice point.</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<!-- 
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Right triangle <m>ABC</m> has a right angle at <m>C</m> and <m>\angle BAC = \theta</m>; the point <m>D</m> is chosen on <m>AB</m> so that <m>AC= AD= 1</m>; the point <m>E</m> is chosen on <m>BC</m> so that <m>\angle CDE = \theta</m>. The perpendicular to <m>BC</m> at <m>E</m> meets <m>AB</m> at <m>F</m>. Evaluate  <m>\lim _{\theta \to 0} EF</m>.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>

</exercise>
 -->
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Consider triangle <m>ABC</m> with the following trisection points,
<ul><li><p><m>P</m> on segment <m>AB</m> closest to <m>B</m></p></li>
<li><p><m>R</m> on segment <m>BC</m> closest to <m>C</m> and</p></li>
<li><p> <m>Q</m> on segment <m>CA</m> closest to <m>A</m>.</p></li>
</ul>
If these points are connected by segments to the opposite vertices of the triangle, is the area of the inner triangle created by the segments related to the area of triangle <m>ABC</m>?</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

</exercises>
</chapter> 