<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- MBX -->
<chapter xml:id="c-games">
<title>Games</title>
<introduction><p>Mathematical games are a common type of problem in the Putnam. The two most recent cases have been difficult, A5 in 2017 and B5 in 2014.  In analyzing games, it is  always assumed that players use optimal strategies, i. e., they make rational moves in their best interests.</p>
</introduction>
<section>
<title>Finite Two Person Games - Nim</title><idx>Nim</idx>
<p>Nim is the name associated with a variety of games in which players take turns removing stones, sticks or some other objects from one or more piles, with the winner normally being the last player who can make a valid move.</p>
<p>Here is one of the simplest versions of Nim. We start with a single pile of stones. Let's say 14.  A valid move for either player is to remove 1, 2 or 3 stones from the pile. That's all there is to the game.  With an initial pile of 14, the first player will aways win.  Here is why:  The first player will remove 2 piles from the pile leaving twelve stones.   Now the second player is free to remove 1, 2, or 3 stones.  Player 1 will respond by removing however many stones are needed to leave player 2 with eight stones.  The long-term strategy for player 1 is to always leave player 2 with a multiple of four stones.   Player 2 can never respond in such a way that player 1's strategy can't be continued.  Eventually, player 2 will be left with four stones.   Clearly player 1 is destined to win.   Of course if the starting number of stones is a multiple of 4, it's player 2 who is destined to win using the same strategy.</p>
<p>Warm-up:  How does the game change if the moves that are allowed are to remove 1, 2 or 4 stones, but not 3 stones?
</p>
</section>  
<section>
<title>Mind Games</title>
<p>Some games cannot really be played in that they would require an infinite number of moves. Other game-related problems ask a long term strategy, such as the following, where playing the game once is not the point.</p>
<example xml:id="example-near-far">
<title>Near-Far</title><idx>Near-Far</idx>
<p>In the game Near-Far, Alpha and Beta each select a point in the closed unit disc. Alpha wins if the points are within 1/2 of each other and Beta wins if they are not. They play the game repeatedly. What is the best strategy for each of them to adopt, and what is the probability of Alpha winning?</p>

<p>It would seem that the best strategy for Beta would be to select a random point on the edge of the disc. Even if Alpha knows this, the best response is to select a point that “covers” as much of the edge as possible. This can be done by selecting a point <m>\sqrt{3}/2</m> units from the center of the disc, covering an arc of length  <m>\pi/3</m>. If they both stick to these stratagem, the probability Alpha wins is <m>\frac{1}{6}</m>. However, Beta can also select the center of the disc, being sure of winning if Alpha sticks to the strategy described above. Knowing this, Alpha should employ a mixed strategy, also selecting the center on occasion. </p>

<p>The mixed strategies can be summarized with a matrix showing the expected pay-off for Alpha.  The C-strategy is to select the center of the disc while the E-strategies are to select a random point on the disc at distances of <m>\sqrt{3}/2</m> and 1 for Alpha and Beta, respectively. </p>
<table>
  <title>
    Mixed Strategy Matrix for Near-Far
  </title>
  <tabular>
    <row>
      <cell>   </cell>
      <cell>   </cell>
      <cell>Beta   </cell>
      <cell>   </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell>   </cell>
      <cell right="medium" bottom="medium">  </cell>
      <cell bottom="medium">  C     </cell>
      <cell bottom="medium">  E      </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell> Alpha  </cell>
      <cell right="medium">  C  </cell>
      <cell right="medium" bottom="medium">  1  </cell>
      <cell bottom="medium">  -1  </cell>
    </row>
    <row>
      <cell>   </cell>
      <cell right="medium"> E  </cell>
      <cell right="medium">-1</cell>
      <cell> <m> -\frac{2}{3}</m>  </cell>
    </row>
  </tabular>
</table>
<p>If Alpha chooses the C-strategy with probability <m>\alpha</m> and Beta chooses C with probability <m>\beta</m>, then the expected payoff for Alpha will be 
<me>A(\alpha,\beta)= \frac{7\alpha \beta}{3}-\frac{\alpha}{3}-\frac{\beta}{3}-\frac{ 2}{3}</me>
This function has a saddle point at <m>\alpha = \beta = \frac{1}{7}</m> and its value there is <m>-\frac{5}{7}</m>, which implies that the probability Alpha wins is <m> \frac{1}{7}</m>.</p> 

</example>
</section>
<section><title>See also</title>
<p>Problem B2 in the February 2021 Putnam.</p>
 <problem
xml:id="exercise-putnam2020b2"> <statement><p>
Let <m>k</m> and <m>n</m> be integers with <m>1 \leq k \lt n</m>. Alice and Bob play a game with <m>k</m> pegs in a line of <m>n</m> holes. At the beginning of the game, the pegs occupy the <m>k</m> leftmost holes. A legal move consists of moving a single peg
to any vacant hole that is further to the right. The players alternate moves, with Alice playing first. The game ends when the pegs are in the <m>k</m> rightmost holes, so whoever is next to play cannot move and therefore loses. For what values
of <m>n</m> and <m>k</m> does Alice have a winning strategy?
</p></statement> 
<solution><p>
We refer to this two-player game, with <m>n</m> holes and <m>k</m> pegs, as the <em><m>(n,k)</m>-game</em>.
We will show that Alice has a winning strategy for the <m>(n,k)</m>-game if and only if at least one of <m>n</m> and <m>k</m> is odd; otherwise Bob has a winning strategy.</p>

<p>We reduce the first claim to the second as follows. If <m>n</m> and <m>k</m> are both odd, then Alice can move the <m>k</m>-th peg to the last hole; this renders the last hole, and the peg in it, totally out of play, thus reducing the <m>(n,k)</m>-game to the <m>(n-1,k-1)</m>-game, for which Alice now has a winning strategy by the second claim. Similarly, if <m>n</m> is odd but <m>k</m> is even, then Alice may move the first peg to the <m>(k+1)</m>-st hole, removing the first hole from play and reducing the <m>(n,k)</m>-game to the <m>(n-1,k)</m> game. Finally, if <m>n</m> is even but <m>k</m> is odd, then Alice can move the first peg to the last hole, taking the first and last holes, and the peg in the last hole, out of play, and reducing the <m>(n,k)</m>-game to the <m>(n-2,k-1)</m>-game.</p>

<p>We now assume <m>n</m> and <m>k</m> are both even and describe a winning strategy for the <m>(n,k)</m>-game for Bob.
Subdivide the <m>n</m> holes into <m>n/2</m> disjoint pairs of adjacent holes. Call a configuration of <m>k</m> pegs \textit{good} if for each pair of holes, both or neither is occupied by pegs, and note that the starting position is good. Bob can ensure that after each of his moves, he leaves Alice with a good configuration: presented with a good configuration, Alice must move a peg from a pair of occupied holes to a hole in an unoccupied pair; then Bob can move the other peg from the first pair to the remaining hole in the second pair, resulting in another good configuration. In particular, this ensures that Bob always has a move to make. Since the game must terminate, this is a winning strategy for Bob.</p>
</p></solution>  </problem>





</section>  
<exercises>
<title>Problems</title>
<exercise><title>Nim Piles</title>
<statement><p>
This game starts with three piles of stones. The piles contain 5, 7, and 11 stones. Two players take turns. On each turn, a player
must remove at least one stone, and may remove any number of stones provided they all come from the same pile. The goal is to be the last player
to take a stone. What player has a definite winning strategy; i. e. will always win if he/she makes the right moves.
</p></statement>
<hint><p>Look closely at these two positions: two piles of three stones, or three piles with three, two and one stone.   These are both losing positions for the next player for the same reason.</p></hint>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>
A line of squares is laid out starting with square 1, then square 2 to its right, square 3 further right, etc.  The number of squares can be as long as you like. Put some coins in some of the squares.  For example.  one on square 1, two on square 3, and one on square 6.  Take turns moving one coin any positive number of squares to the left. There are no restrictions otherwise. You can jump onto or over other coins, or jump clear off the line. You can have any number of coins on a square. Your aim is to be the person who makes the last move.   If players 1 and 2 alternate moves with player 1 going first, who will win?    
</p></statement>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>
Two players play the following game. They start with two piles of candy, one with 21 and the other with 20 candies. At each turn, a player eats one of the piles and splits the other into two piles. The first player who can't make a legal move loses. Who will win, the first player or the second
player?
</p></statement>
<hint><p>If you leave our opponent with two <q>piles</q> with one candy each, you win.</p></hint>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>
Two players play the following game. Start with the equation
           <me>\_ x^3 + \_ x^2 + \_ x + \_= 0</me>
The players take turns writing real numbers instead of blanks. The first player wins if the resulting cubic equation has exactly one real solution; otherwise he loses. Does either player have a winning strategy?
</p></statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
 -->
<solution><p>We identify the blanks, from left to right as a, b, c and d.  Player 2 will always win using the following strategy.</p>
<p>We pair up the blanks  a and c, and b and d.   Whatever blank Player 1 fills, Player 2 should fill in the other blank in the pair with the negation of the number Player 1 used.  For example, if Player fills blank c with a 2, Player 2 should fill blank a with -2.  After four turns, the result is 
	<me>s x^3 + t x^2 - s x - t =  (x^2-1)(s x + t) =0</me> 
which always has 3 real solutions if both <m>s</m>  and <m>t</m> are nonzero.   If any combination of  <m>s</m>  and <m>t</m> are zero, it's easy to see that the number of real solutions is not 1.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>
Consider the following game played by players A and B with a deck of <m>2n</m> cards numbered from 1 to <m>2n</m>. The deck is randomly shuffled and <m>n</m> cards are dealt to each of two players. Beginning with A, the players take turns discarding one of the remaining cards of their choice and announcing its number. The game ends as soon as the sum of the numbers on the discarded cards is divisible by <m>2n + 1</m>. The last person to discard wins the game. Assuming optimal strategy by both A and B, what is the probability that A wins?
</p></statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p>Putnam 1993 B2</p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>
 Alice and Bob play a game in which they take turns removing stones from a heap that initially has <m>n</m> stones. The number of stones removed at each turn must be one less than a prime. The winner is the player who takes the last stone. Alice plays first. Prove that there are infinitely many <m>n</m> such that Bob has a winning strategy.
</p></statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
 -->
<solution><p>The way to think about this game that if Alice has a winning position and makes any move, she has to put Bob into one of her losing positions.  Therefore if the game starts with <m>n</m> stones, there must be a prime <m>p</m> such that <m>n-(p-1)</m> is a losing position for Bob.  Therefore, if the game starts with <m>n-(p-1)</m> stones and it's Alice's turn, Bob will win.</p>
<p>Assume Bob has only a finite set of initial pile sizes for which he wins, <m>B={n_1,n_2, \dots, n_M}</m>, where <m>N=max(n_i)</m>.  This means that for every <m>n \notin B</m>, Alice can leave Bob with a number of stones in <m>B</m>.
<me>
\begin{split}
	n \notin B &amp; \Rightarrow  n = n_k + (p-1)  \textrm{  for some prime }p\\
	 &amp;  \Rightarrow  n-p \lt N
\end{split}
</me>
Therefore, for all <m>n \geq N</m>, <m>n</m> differs from a prime by a some bounded value.  Since there are arbitrarily long runs of non-primes, this is a contradiction. </p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>
In  Determinant Tic-Tac-Toe, Player 1 enters a 1 in an empty <m>3\times 3</m> matrix. Player 0 counters with a 0 in a vacant position, and play
continues in turn until the <m>3 \times  3</m> matrix is completed with five 1's and four 0's. Player 0 wins if the determinant is 0 and player 1 wins otherwise. Assuming both players pursue optimal strategies, who will win and how?
</p></statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement><p>
Alice and Barbara play a game with a pack of <m>2n</m> cards, on each of which is written a positive integer. There is no restriction on the size of integers and whether they repeat or not.   The pack is shuffled and the cards laid out in a row, with the numbers facing upwards. Alice starts, and the girls take turns to remove one card from either end of the row, until Barbara picks up the final card. Each girl's score is the sum of the numbers on her chosen cards at the end of the game. High score wins.  Is either player sure to win?
</p></statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
 -->
<solution><p>Alice is sure to win if the sum of the card values in odd positions in the line differs from the sum on even positions. If that is the case, assume the odd positions have a higher sum.  Alice will win by choosing the card in position 1.  Barbara is forced to choose a card in an even position and then Alice can take a card from the exposed odd position.  By continuing in this way, Alice will get all the cards in odd positions and win.  There are some initial configurations where the game will end in a tie.  For example, if <m>n=2</m> the line of cards <m> 2,1,3,4</m> will produce a tie.</p></solution>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>
A game is played as follows. The first player selects an interval <m>[a, b]</m>. The second player selects an interval <m>[c, d] \subset  [a, b]</m>. The first
player selects an interval inside <m>[c, d]</m>, and so on. The game goes on forever. The first player will win if the intersection of all segments contains a rational number. Is he going to win?
</p></statement>
<hint><p>The key is that the rationals are countably infinite while the irrationals are not.</p></hint>
<solution><p>The second player can make a list of rational numbers in <m>[a,b]</m> and plan to avoid them sequentially while assuring that the limit of the lengths of the intervals converges to zero.  The intersection of all intervals in the game is then a set with a single real number.  Since no rational number can be in the intersection that single number must be irrational.</p></solution>

</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>
Players 2 and 3 alternate removing stones in a nim-type game with player 2 going first and winner being the one to remove the last stone. Player 2 may remove either 1 or 2 stones in any move and Player 3 can remove either 1 or 3 stones in any move.  If the pile starts with <m>n</m> stones, for what value of <m>n</m> will Player 2 win the game?
</p></statement>
<hint><p>Player 3 can never remove an even number of stones.</p></hint>
<solution><p>Player 2 will always win by leaving Player 3 an even number of stones.</p></solution>
</exercise>
</exercises>
</chapter>