<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- MBX -->
<chapter xml:id="c-induction-pigeons">
<title>Induction and Pigeonholes </title>
<introduction>
	<p>Mathematical induction and the pigeonhole principle are two common proof techniques that students should have seen.  They are good warm-up topic for the first class.	</p>
	</introduction>
<section xml:id="s-induction">
<title>Mathematical Induction</title>
	<p>We illustrate a basic proof by induction by proving Fermat's Little Theorem. </p>

	<theorem xml:id="theorem-fermat-little"><title>Fermat's Little Theorem</title>
	<idx>Fermat's Little Theorem</idx>
	<statement><p>Let <m>p</m> be a prime number, and <m>n</m> an integer. Then <m>n^p - n</m> is divisible by <m>p</m>.</p>
	</statement>
	<proof><p>The Theorem is clearly true for the case of <m>p=2</m> since any integer and its square have the same odd/even parity and their difference must be even.   We now assume that <m>p</m> is odd.   The theorem is clearly true for <m>n=0</m>.  This forms the basis for an induction poof for positive values of <m>n</m>.  Assume for some <m>n \geq 0</m>, that  <m>n^p - n</m> is divisible by <m>p</m>.  Now consider  <m>(n+1)^p - (n+1)</m>.
<md>
  <mrow>(n+1)^p - (n+1) \amp=   \left( n^p+\sum_{k=1}^{p-1} { \binom{p}{k} n^{p-k} } + 1\right) -n -1 </mrow>
  <mrow>                \amp= (n^p -n)  +\sum_{k=1}^{p-1} {\binom{p}{k} n^{p-k} }</mrow>
</md>
</p>
<p>The first term is divisible by <m>p</m> by the induction hypothesis, and the the second is also divisible by <m>p</m> because <m>\binom{p}{k}</m> is divisible by <m>p</m> for <m>k = 1, 2,\dots,p-1</m>.  Therefore, the theorem is true for all positive values of <m>n</m>.  Finally, given the truth of the theorem for positive integers, it is clearly true for negative values.</p> 
</proof>
</theorem>
<p>There may appear to be gaps in the proof from the point of view of a typical undergraduate course. Saying as we did at the end that something is clearly true may not be acceptable to some instructors in some courses.  However, in the context of preparing for the Putnam, knowing how basic your arguments need to be is important.  In this author's opinion the negative case is sufficiently obvious to skip the details. The same is true of the statement that <m>\binom{p}{k}</m> is divisible by <m>p</m> for <m>k = 1, 2,\dots,p-1</m>.</p>
<p>Our next example will be about connected undirected planar graphs.</p>
<list><title>What do these words mean?</title>
<dl>
<li><title>Undirected</title><p>Edges have no direction assigned, normally represented as a two element subset of the vertex set.</p></li>
<li><title>Connected</title><p>For any two vertices, there is a sequence of edges that provide a path between them.</p></li>
<li><title>Planar</title><p>It is possible to draw the graph on a plane so that no two edges cross.</p></li>
</dl>
</list> 
<p><xref ref="cup-graph" text="type-local"/> is an example of one such graph.</p>

            <figure xml:id="cup-graph">
                <caption>An example of a connected undirected planar graph
                </caption>
                <image source="images/cup-graph.png">
                    <description>A connected undirected planar graph.</description>
                </image>
            </figure>
<example>
<title> Euler's Formula</title><idx> Euler's Formula</idx>
<p>Euler's Formula states that if <m>G</m> is a connected undirected planar graph, with <m>v</m> vertices, <m>e</m> edges and <m>r</m> regions, then <m>v+r-e=2</m></p>

<p>We will prove this by induction on the number of edges in the graph.  Let <m>p(n)</m> be <q>The statement is true for all such graphs with <m>n</m> edges, where <m>n\geq 0</m>.</q></p>

<p>Basis:  If a connected undirected planar graph has zero edges, it must be that the graph has only one vertex and the plane is  <q>divided</q> into only one region.  Therefore <m>v=1</m>, <m>e=0</m>, and <m>r=1</m>; and   <m>v+r-e=1+1-0 =2</m>.</p>
<p>Induction.  Assume Euler's formula is true for all connected undirected planar graphs  with <m>k</m> edges where <m>k\leq n</m>.   Assume we such a graph, <m>G</m>, with <m>n+1</m> edges.  We remove one of the edges from <m>G</m>, making it an undirected planar graph with <m>n</m> edges.  However it may no longer be connected.  We need to consider two possible cases.</p>

<p>Case 1:  The graph with the removed edge is still connected. In the example above, if we remove <m>e_1</m>, we have this situation.  Since we have
a connected undirected planar graph with <m>n</m> edges, the induction hypothesis applied with <m>k=n</m>, and so Euler's formula is true.  Now, consider
returning the edge we had removed.  In so doing, the number of edges increases by 1, the number of verticies stays the same, and the number of
regions increases by 1 since the returned edge divides a region into two parts.  Therefore, the net change in the expression <m>v+r-e</m> is <m>0+1-1=0</m>and
so it is still equal to 2.</p>
<p>Case 2: The graph with the removed edge has two components. In the example above, if we remove <m>e_2</m>, we have this situation.   The vertices
in each of the two components are connected.  Assume the components have <m>k_1</m> and <m>k_2</m> edges, where <m>k_1+k_2= n</m>.  Furthermore, assume
the numbers of vertices and regions in the first component is <m>v_1</m> and <m>r_1</m>, while the second component has <m>v_2</m> and <m>r_2</m> for it{'}s
vertices and regions. By the induction hyponthesis,
<me>v_1+r_1-k_1=2 \textrm{ and } v_2+r_2-k_2=2</me>
Now when we bring back the edge we had removed, the original graph had <m>v_1+ v_2</m> vertices and <m>k_1+k_2+1= n+1</m> edges.  The number of regions is <m>r_1+ r_2-1</m> because the infinite regions of the two components  is now one region.  Collecting this information, we have 
<me>\begin{split}
	v+r-e &amp;= \left(v_1+v_2\right)+\left(r_1+ r_2-1\right) -\left(k_1+k_2+1\right)\\
		&amp; = \left(v_1+r_1-k_1\right)+ \left(v_2+r_2+k_2\right) -2\\
		&amp;=2+2-2 = 2
	\end{split}</me>
Therefore Euler's formula is true for this case.</p>
</example>

<example xml:id="determinant-sage-assist"><title>Recursive Thinking</title>
<p>Consider the sequence of  matrices <m>A(n)</m> defined by <m>A(1)=[1]</m> and for <m>n \ge 1</m>, <m>A(n)</m> is an <m>(n-1) \times (n-1)</m> identity matrix with a column of 1's appended to it, and then a row of 1's appended.  For example,
<m>A(3)=\begin{pmatrix}1 &amp; 0 &amp; 1\\
							  0 &amp; 1 &amp; 1\\
							  1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \end{pmatrix}</m>.
What is the determinant of <m>A(n)</m>?</p>
<p>To solve this problem, we can expand the determinant along the first row.  This gives us two minors to evalute, one of which is the determinant of <m>A(n-1)</m>.  The other minor is a matrix that takes a form like this one, in the case were we are expanding <m>\lvert A(5)\rvert</m>: <m>\begin{pmatrix}
							  0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0\\
							  0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0\\
							  0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1\\
							  1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 &amp; 1 \end{pmatrix}</m>.</p>
<p>By shifting the bottom row up, one row at a time, with <m>n-2</m> shifts, we get an upper triangular matrix with all 1's in the diagonal, and so the minor is  <m>(-1)^{(n-2)}</m>  The cofactor corresponding to this minor will have a sign <m>(-1)^{n+1}</m>.  Therefore the value of the cofactor will be <m>(-1)^{n+1}\cdot (-1)^{(n-2)}= -1</m> and so we have
<me>\lvert A(n) \rvert = \lvert A(n-1) \rvert -1</me>.  Since <m>\lvert A(1) \rvert = 1</m>, we conclude that <m>\lvert A(n) \rvert = 2-n </m></p>							  


<p>Occasionally, an assist from technology will jump-start a solution.  In this example, it might not be necessary. However, here is a verification that our solution was correct, or if you hadn't seen the recursion, it might serve as a hint.   Change the value of <c>n</c> to see how the determinant depends on it.</p>
<sage>
<input>
n=5
A=Matrix([[i==j or i==n-1 or j==n-1 for i in range(n)] for j in range(n)] )
[A,det(A)]
</input>
<output>
[[1 0 0 0 1]
[0 1 0 0 1]
[0 0 1 0 1]
[0 0 0 1 1]
[1 1 1 1 1], -3]
</output>
</sage>
</example>


</section>  
<section xml:id="s-pigeons">
<title>The Pigeonhole Principle</title>

            <figure xml:id="to-many-pigeons">
                <caption>More pigeons than pigeonholes
                </caption>
                <image source="images/TooManyPigeons.jpg">
                    <description>An array of nine pigeonholes occupied by ten pigeons. This image by en:User:McKay CC-BY-SA-3.0 via Wikimedia Commons</description>
                </image>
            </figure>
 


<p>Informally, the Pigeonhole Principle says that if you have more pigeons than you have pigeonholes, then at least one pair of pigeons have to share the same pigeonhole. The trick to using this simple idea is to identify the pigeons and pigeonholes in a problem.  Here is a relatively simple example. A clue that we can use the Pigeonhole Principle problem in this case is that we are asked to prove the existence of two objects that share a property.</p> 
	<example xml:id="e-pigeons-1">
		<p>Prove that every set of 10 two-digit integer numbers has two disjoint subsets with the same sum of elements. (Subsets are pigeons, possible sums are holes)</p>
		<p>We want two subsets with the same sum, so consider the possible sums to be pigeonholes, and now picture subsets of our ten integer set to be the pigeons. We are not given a specific set of integers, but we can identify the range of possible sums of elements in their subsets.  The smallest sum is 10 while the largest proper subset is <m>91+92+\cdots+99 =855 </m>. That gives us 846 pigeonholes.  There are <m>2^{10}-2 = 1022 &gt; 845</m> non-empty proper subsets of a ten element set.  Therefore, if we imagine each subset to roost with its sum, we are sure there there must be two subsets with the same sum.  Now those two subsets may not be disjoint, but if we simply remove elements in their intersection, we are done.
		</p>
	</example>
</section>  
<exercises xml:id="induction-exercises">
<title>Problems</title>

<exercise number="1">
<statement>
<p>Find and prove a formula for the sum of the first <m>n</m> consecutive odd positive integers. For example, if <m>n = 4</m> then <m>1 + 3 + 5 + 7 = 16</m>.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Look at the first few examples.</p>
</hint>
<solution><p>First a bit of advice: It is often much easier to write a solution by <q>inventing</q> notation.  In this case, instead of referring to <q>the sum of the first <m>n</m> consecutive odd positive integers,</q> we define <m>s(n)</m> to be that sum.</p>
<p>We claim that <m>s(n)=n^2</m>.  There are many proofs of this fact.  First we observe that the <m>k</m>th odd positive integer is <m>2k-1</m> and so <m>s(n)=\sum_{k=1}^n 2k-1</m></p>
<p>The basis is clearly true:  <m>s(1)=\sum_{k=1}^1 2k-1 = 1 = 1^2</m>.</p>
<p>Now assume that for some <m>n\geq 1</m> we have <m>s(n)=n^2</m>.  Then
<me> s(n+1) = \sum_{k=1}^{n+1} 2k-1= s(n) + 2n + 1 = n^2 + 2n +1 = (n+1)^2.</me>
This completes the induction proof.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise number="2">
<statement>
<p>
	Prove that in a room with <m>n</m> people, at least two people know exactly the same number of people. Assume knowing is a symmetric relation: If Paul knows Pat, then Pat knows Paul.
</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>It is impossible to have someone know <m>n-1</m> people and someone else know nobody in the room.</p>
</hint>
</exercise>
<exercise number="3">
<statement>
	<p>
		Let <m>S</m> be any set of 18 distinct integers chosen from the arithmetic progression <m>1, 4, 7, \dots , 100</m>. Prove that there must be two integers in <m>S</m> whose sum is 101.
	</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Count the number of pairs that can add up to 101.</p>
</hint>
<solution><p>Note that <m>S</m> is drawn from <m>\{3i + 1 \vert 0 \leq i \leq 33 \}</m>, which contains 34 integers that can be paired up in such a way that if <m>i + j = 33</m>, then  <m>(1+3i)+ (1+3j)=101</m>.  There are 17 such pairs, and so of the 18 elements in <m>S</m>, at least one of the pairs that add to 101 must be included.</p> 
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise number="4">
<statement>
	<p>
		Choose 51 positive integers from 1 to 100. Prove that one of them is a multiple of another.
	</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Each integer has a maximal odd factor.</p>
</hint>
<solution>
<p>For each integer is in <m> A = \{1, 2, 3, \dots, 100\}</m> is equal to <m>2^k m</m>, where <m>m</m> is an odd integer in <m>B= \{1, 3, 5, \dots, 99\}</m>.  Since <m>\lvert B \rvert =50</m> and we have selected 51 integers from <m>A</m>, there must be two in <m>B</m> with the form <m>2^j n</m> and <m>2^k n</m>, where <m>j \lt k</m> and <m>n \in B</m>, and we have the second as a multiple of the first.
</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise number="5">
<statement>
<p>
	Show that a <m>2^n \times  2^n</m> square with a corner tile removed can be covered without overlaps by L-shaped figures (each figure contains 3 tiles). (If you feel adventurous, how about an <m>n \times  n</m> square for arbitrary <m>n</m>?)
</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise number="6">
<statement>
	<p>
		Given nine points inside the unit square, with no three colinear, prove that some three of them form a triangle whose area does not exceed <m>1/8</m>.
	</p>

</statement>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise number="7">
<statement>
<p>Prove that every positive integers is the sum of distinct Fibonacci numbers.
</p>
</statement>
<solution><p>We an prove this by induction. Starting with any positive integer, we remove the largest possible Fibonacci number to simplify the problem.  Our only concern is whether we would possibly need one of the Fibonacci numbers more than once.  Start by observing that 1 is a Fibonacci number.  Now assume that  all <m>k</m>, <m>1 \leq k \leq n</m> are the sum of distinct Fibonacci numbers.   Consider <m>n+1</m>.  We are done if <m>n+1</m> is a Fibonacci number.   Otherwise, it is between Fibonacci numbers:  
<md><mrow>F_m \lt n+1 \lt F_{m+1}</mrow>
<mrow>\quad \RightArrow \quad 0\lt(n+1)-F_m \lt F_{m+1}-F_m = F_{m-1}.</mrow></md>
Therefore <m>F_m</m> is not needed any longer and we apply the induction hypothesis. Notice that we also will not need <m>F_{m-1}</m> since our difference is less than it.  This prove a stronger result, that the distinct Fibonacci numbers that we need are non-consecutive. </p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise number="8">
<statement>
<p>
	Inside a circle of radius 4 are chosen 61 points. Show that among them there are two at distance at most <m>\sqrt{2}</m> from each other.
</p>

</statement>
<solution><p>Solution 1:  If the center of the circle is placed at the origin of the Cartesian plane, we see that the interior can be divided into 60  one by one squares and partial squares.  Since there are 61 points, the Pigeonhole Principle can be applied, were any rule would be applied to point on the boundary of squares.</p>
<p>Solution 2:  For each point, place a disk of radius <m>\frac{\sqrt{2}}{2}</m> centered at that point. The area of each disk is <m>\frac{\pi}{2}</m>.  The 61 disks cover a total area of <m>\frac{61\pi}{2}</m>.  These disks are contained within a circle of area <m>(4+ \frac{\sqrt{2}}{2})^2 \pi</m> which is less than <m>\frac{61\pi}{2}</m>.  Therefore two of the disks must overlap and so their centers must be within <m>\sqrt{2},</m> of one another.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise number="9">
<statement>
<p>Show that there is a positive term of the Fibonacci sequence that is divisible by 1000. Recall that the Fibonacci sequence is defined by <m>F_0=0</m>, <m>F_1= 1</m> and for <m>n>1</m>, <m>F_n= F_{n-1}+F_{n-2}</m>. Note: The starting values of 0 and 1 are often replaced with 1 and 1, but for this problem it's slightly easier to structure a proof.
</p>

</statement>
<hint><p>Start with two pairs of consecutive terms that have identical remainders mod 1000.</p>
</hint>
</exercise>
<exercise number="10">
<statement>
	<p>You have coins <m>C_1</m>, <m>C_2</m>, ... , <m>C_n</m>. For each <m>k</m>, <m>C_k</m> is biased so that, when tossed, it has probability <m>1/(2k + 1)</m> of falling heads. If the <m>n</m> coins are tossed, what is the probability that the number of heads is odd? Express the answer as a rational function of <m>n</m>.
	</p>

</statement>
<answer><p>The probability that the number of heads is odd is <m>\frac{n}{2n+1}.</m></p></answer>
 <solution><p>Let <m>p_n</m> be the probability that after tossing the first <m>n</m> coins, an odd number of heads have appeared.  Clearly <m>p_1 = \frac{1}{3}</m>.  If <m>n \gt 1</m>,
 	<me>\begin{split}
 		p_n &amp;= \frac{1}{2n+1}  (1-p_{n-1}) + \frac{2n}{2n+1} p_{n-1}\\
 			&amp; = \frac{2n-1}{2n+1}p_{n-1} + \frac{1}{2n+1}
 		\end{split}
 		</me>
If you use the formula to compute a few more terms of the sequence, the pattern <m>p_n=\frac{n}{2n+1} </m> emerges and this can be proven by induction.
 </p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise number="11">
<statement>
<p>
	Prove that any positive integer can be represented as <m>\pm 1^2\pm 2^2\pm 3^2\pm \cdots \pm n^2</m> for some positive integer <m>n</m> and some choice of signs. 
</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<solution><p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise number="12">
<statement>
<p>
	A fair coin is tossed repeatedly until there is a run of an odd number of heads followed by a tail. Determine the expected number of tosses.
</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Identify beginnings of the process that either end it or <q>reset</q> it.</p></hint>
<solution><p>If the first flip produces a tail, the expected length of the process from then on is the same as the expectation before that flip.   The same is true if the first two flips come up heads.  If the first two flips are heads-tails, the process has ended in two flips.  One of these three possible beginnings will occur with probabilities <m>1/2</m>, <m>1/4</m>, and <m>1/4</m>, respectively.  Therefore if <m>F</m> is the expected number of flips, we have
<me>\frac{1}{2} (1+F) +\frac{1}{4} (2+F) +\frac{1}{4} (2) = F</me>.
Solving for <m>F</m>, we get 6 for the expected number of flips.  </p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>Show that every set of <m>n</m> integers has a nonempty subset such that the sum of its elements is divisible by <m>n</m>.</p></statement>
<solution><p>
Let <m>a_1, a_2, \dots , a_n</m> be the integers and let <m>s_1, s_2, \dots , s_n</m> be the partial sums, <m>s_k=\sum _{i=1}^k
a_i</m>.  If one of the sums is divisible by <m>n</m> then we are done, so assume none are multiples of <m>n</m>.  By the pigeonhole principle,
there must be two partial sums that have the same residue mod <m>n</m>.  Let <m>l \lt m </m> be such that 
	<me>s_l\equiv s_m \pmod{n} \Rightarrow s_m-s_l= \sum _{k=l+1}^m a_k=n q</me> for some integer <m>q</m>.  Therefore the set we are looking for is <m>\left\{a_{l+1}, \ldots, a_m\right\}</m>.
</p></solution>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>Show that for any polynomial <m>f(x)</m> over the integers with degree <m>d\lt n</m>, we have <m>\sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k \binom{n}{k} f(k) = 0</m>.</p></statement>
<solution>
<p>(Solution by Tung Nguyen) Proof by induction on <m>d</m>. Denote <m>f(x) = \sum_{i = 0}^{d} a_i x^i</m>, where <m>a_i</m> are integer coefficients.  If <m>d=0</m>, then functions <m>f(x)</m> of degree 0 are constant, i.e. <m>f(x) = c</m> for some <m>c \in \mathbb{Z}</m>. This leads to
<men xml:id="sum0">\begin{split}
\sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}f(k) &amp; = \sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}c\\
		&amp; = c\sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}(1)^{n-k} \\
		&amp; = c(1 - 1)^n = 0
\end{split}
</men>
for all positive integers <m>n \gt 0 = d</m>. Note at if <m>n = 0</m> the sum above is <m>c</m> instead of <m>0</m>.</p>
<p>Assume that the formula is true for every polynomial of degree <m>d</m> and applicable to all <m>n \in \mathbb{N}</m> satisfying <m>d \lt n - 1</m>. We will prove that the formula is true for <m>d + 1 \lt n</m>.</p>
<p>Let <m>g(x)</m> be an arbitrary polynomial of degree <m>d+1</m> over the integers, then <m>g(x)</m> can be rewritten as <m>g(x) = x\cdot h(x) + c</m>, where <m>h(x)</m> has degree <m>d</m> and <m>c</m> is an integer. Then
<men xml:id="sum1">
\begin{split}
\sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}g(k) &amp;= \sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}\left[kh(k) + c\right]\\
		&amp; = \sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}k \cot h(k) + \sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}c.
\end{split}
</men>
The second term is 0 which is proven by <xref ref="sum0"/>, while 

<men xml:id="sum2">\begin{split}
\sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}k\cdot h(k) 
	&amp;= (-1)^0\binom{n}{0}0\cdot h(0) + \sum_{k=1}^{n} (-1)^k\frac{n!}{k!(n-k)!}k\cdot h(k)\\
	&amp; = 0 + \sum_{k=1}^{n} (-1)^k\frac{n!}{(k-1)!(n-k)!}h(k)\\
	&amp; = -n\sum_{k=1}^{n} (-1)^{k-1}\frac{(n-1)!}{(k-1)!(n-k)!}h(k) \\ 
	&amp;= -n\sum_{k=1}^{n} (-1)^{k-1}\binom{n-1}{k-1}h(k)\\
	&amp; = -n\sum_{k=0}^{n-1} (-1)^k\binom{n-1}{k}h(k+1)
\end{split}</men></p>
<p>Because <m>h(x)</m> has degree <m>d</m>, <m>h(x+1)</m> is also has degree <m>d</m>, which is less than <m>n - 1</m> by the induction hypothesis. Therefore we have 
<men xml:id="sum3">\sum_{k=0}^{n-1} (-1)^k\binom{n-1}{k}h(k+1)  = 0 </men>
</p>
<p>Combining <xref ref="sum1" text="local"/>,<xref ref="sum2" text="local"/> and <xref ref="sum3" text="local"/> together, we have 
<m>\sum_{k=0}^{n} (-1)^k\binom{n}{k}g(k) = 0</m>. Because <m>g(x)</m> is arbitrarily chosen, the formula must be true for all polynomials of degree <m>d + 1 \lt n</m>, completing the induction.
</p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Given a sequence of integers <m>x_1</m>, <m>x_2</m>, <m>\dots x_n</m> whose sum is 1, prove that exactly one of the cyclic shifts
<md>
<mrow> x_1,x_2,\dots ,x_n </mrow>
<mrow>  x_2,\dots,x_n,x_1  </mrow>
<mrow> \vdots    </mrow>
<mrow> x_n,x_1,\dots,x_{n-1}  </mrow>
</md>
has all of its partial sums positive. (By a partial sum we mean the sum of the first <m>k</m> terms, <m>k \leq  n</m>.
</p>

</statement>
<solution><p>We define a <q>good shift</q> to be one for which the partial sums are all positive. The property we wish to prove is obviously true for <m>n=1</m>.  Now assume that for some <m>n \geq 1</m> that it's true for all sequences of length <m>n</m>.  Consider an integer sequence of length <m>n+1</m>.  Since the sum of the terms is 1, there must exist at least one negative term and among them all, there must be one that is preceded by a positive term. We can assume that these two terms are at the end of the sequence, <m>x_n, x_{n+1}</m>.  Now consider the sequence of length <m>n</m> defined by <m>y_j = x_j</m> if <m>j \lt n</m>  and  <m>y_n=x_n+x_{n+1}</m>.  By the induction hypothesis, this sequence has a unique good shift.  In that shifted sequence, wherever <m>y_n</m> is located  we replace it with the two terms <m>x_n, x_{n+1}</m>. The partial sums of this expanded sequence are still all positive so we have a good shift of the original sequence.  Finally, we see that this good shift is unique. Every good shift of the original sequence can produce a good shift of the reduced <m>y</m>-sequence and we know that only one of those exists.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
</exercises>
</chapter> 