<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- MBX -->

<chapter xml:id="c-number_theory">
<title>Number Theory </title>
<introduction><p>The starting point for number theory is the set of positive integers.  After developing basic arithmetic properties of this set, number theory goes in countless directions and is one of the richest of all mathematical subjects. Here, we touch on just a few key ideas.</p></introduction>
<section>
<title>Primes</title>
<p>A prime are positive integer greater than one that are only divisible by one and itself. A fundamental theorem in number theory states that every positive integer greater than one is uniquely factorable as a product of one or more primes.</p>
<p>You should be familiar with the fact that there are an infinite number of primes, and if pressed, should be able to prove it.  There is only one even prime, 2. If we divide an odd prime by 4, the remainder will either be 1 or 3; so every odd prime has the form <m>4k+1</m> or <m>4k+3</m>.  Here is a proof that there are an infinite number of primes of the second form. Suppose, to the contrary, that there are only a finite number of primes of the form <m>4k+3</m>, and that they are  <m>p_1=4k_1+3</m>, <m>p_2=4k_2+3, \dots</m>, <m>p_r=4k_r+3</m>.  Consider the integer <m>Q= 4(p_1 \cdot p_2 \cdot \cdots \cdot p_r)+3</m>.  We observe that <m>Q</m> is an odd integer that is not divisible by any of the <m>p_i</m>. It can be factored into a product of primes that are not in the set of <m>p_i</m> but the factors cannot all be of the form <m>4k+1</m> and so there is yet another prime of the form <m>4k+3</m> that was not accounted for in our list of such primes.  This contradiction implies that the set of these integer must be infinite. </p>

<p>We had just proven an instance of a more general theorem called <em>Dirichlet's Theorem</em>, which states that if <m>4k+3</m> is replaced with <m>\alpha k + \beta</m> where <m>\gcd(\alpha,\beta)=1</m> we get the same conclusion, that there are an infinite number of primes of that form.</p>
</section>
<section>
<title>Residues</title>
<p>The residues of integers modulo <m>n</m>, <m>n \geq 2</m> are the remainders upon dividing integers by <m>n</m>.  We start with a simple use of residues.</p>
<example xml:id="mod7">
<p>Show that <m>n^2+ 1</m> is divisible by 7 for no positive integer <m>n</m>.
</p>
<p><me>
	\begin{split}
	 7 \mid (n^2+1) &amp; \Leftrightarrow n^2 \equiv -1\pmod{7}\\
 						 &amp; \Leftrightarrow n^2 \equiv  6\pmod{7}\\
 	\end{split}
 	</me>
We can easily verify that for any <m>n</m>, the residue of <m>n^2\pmod{7}</m> is never 6.</p>
</example>

<example xml:id="example-crt"><title>Chinese Remainder Theorem</title>
<idx>Chinese Remainder Theorem</idx>
<p>Let <m>a, b</m> be integers and <m>m, n</m> positive integers such that <m>\gcd (m,n)=1</m>. Then there is a unique integer, <m>x</m>, in the set
<m>\{0,1,2,\ldots , m n -1\}</m> such that <m>x\equiv a \pmod{m}</m> and
 <m>x\equiv b\pmod{n}</m>.</p>
<p>In order for an integer to satisfy the first conguence, we need <m>x = a + m\cdot q_1</m> for some integer <m>q_1</m>.  Substitution into the second congruence gives us 
<me> a + m\cdot q_1\equiv b \pmod{n} \Rightarrow  m\cdot q_1\equiv b-a \pmod{n}</me>
We know that since <m>m</m> and <m>n</m> are relatively prime, there exist integers <m>s</m> and <m>t</m> such that <me>m \cdot s + n \cdot t = 1  \Rightarrow   m \cdot s \equiv 1 \pmod{n}</me>
and so 
<me>q_1\equiv s(b-a) \pmod{n}  \Rightarrow   x = a + m\cdot (s(b-a)+ n q_2)= x = a + m\cdot s\cdot(b-a)+ (m\cdot n) q_2 </me>
for some integer <m>q_2</m>. This set of solutions constitutes one residue class mod <m>m \cdot n</m> and so there is a unique solution in the desired set.</p>
</example>

</section>  
<section>
<title>Euler's Theorem</title>
<p></p>


<example xml:id="power-mod-21">
<p>Compute <m>5^{159} \pmod{21}</m>.</p>
<p>  </p>
</example>
<theorem><title>Euler's Theorem</title>
<idx>Euler's Theorem</idx>
<statement><p>Let <m>n</m> be a positive integer greater than 1 and <m>a</m> a positive integer that is relatively prime to <m>n</m>.  Then  <m>a^{\phi(n)} \equiv 1 \pmod{n}</m></p></statement>
<proof>
</proof>
</theorem>
<example xml:id="ex-euler-app"><title>__</title>
<p></p>
</example>

</section>  

<exercises>
<title>Problems</title>
<introduction><p>Before starting these problems, you might want to review the statement of <xref ref="theorem-fermat-little" text="title"/>.</p></introduction>
<exercise number="1">
<statement>
<p>We say that two positive rational numbers <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> and <m>\frac{c}{d}</m> are <em>close</em> if <m>b c - ad = \pm 1</m>.  
<ol label="(a)">
	<li><p>Prove that if <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> and <m>\frac{c}{d}</m> are close, then <m>\frac{a+c}{b+d}</m> is close to both <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> and <m>\frac{c}{d}</m>.</p></li>
	<li><p>Find five rational numbers that are close to <m>\frac{2}{7}</m>.</p></li>
	<li><p>Find a connection between pairs of close rational numbers, <m>\frac{a}{b}</m> and <m>\frac{c}{d}</m>, and  the determinant of the matrix 
			<m>\left(
			\begin{array}{cc}
			a  &amp;  b   \\
			c  &amp;  d   \\
			\end{array}
			\right)
			</m>
</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution>
<p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise number="2">
<statement>
<p>Prove that some positive integral power of 17 ends in 0001 (base 10).</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution>
<p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise number="3">
<statement>
<p>Show, without using a calculator, that <m>2^9 + 2^{99}</m> is divisible by 100.</p></statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution>
<p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise number="4"><statement><p>Find a Pythagorean triple that includes the number 2021 as a side length.</p></statement>
<hint>
<p><m>2025</m> is a perfect square.</p>  
</hint>
<answer><m>(2021,180,2029)</m></answer>
<solution><p>Since <m>2021 = 2025-4 = 45^2 - 2^2</m>, we can generate a Pythagorian triple from the general form <m>(b^2-a^2, 2 a b, b^2 + a^2)</m> to get the triple <m>(2021,180,2029)</m>. </p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise number="5">
<statement>
<p>Let <m>\varphi(k)</m> be the number of integers in the set <m>\{1,2, \ldots  , k-1\}</m> that are relatively prime to <m>k</m>.
<ol>
<li><p> Find and prove a formula for <m>\varphi \left(p^n\right)</m> if <m>n\geq 1</m> and <m>p</m> is prime.</p></li>
<li><p>Prove that if <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are relatively prime positive integers greater than <m>1</m>, then  <m>\varphi(a \cdot b)=\varphi(a) \cdot \varphi(b)</m></p></li>
<li><p> Determine the value of <m>\varphi(100!)</m>.</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>

 -->
</exercise>

<exercise number="6">
<statement>
<p>For which positive integers <m>n</m> is there a sum of <m>n</m> consecutive integers that is a perfect square?
</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution>
<p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise number="7">
<statement>
<p>Show that the equation <m>x^2- y^2=2x y z</m> has no solutions in the positive integers. Hint: 
</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Consider a prime divisor of <m>x y</m>.</p></hint>
<!-- 
<solution>
<p></p>
</solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise number="8">
<statement><p>In <xref ref="example-riemann-limit" />, we showed an example of how to deal with floor/ceiling functions. Here is an problem from the 1983 Putnam that can be solved by starting with a similar approach.  We quote the problem verbatim, where <m>[x]</m> was used for the floor function. </p>
<p>Let <m>f(n)=n +[\sqrt{n}]</m> where <m>[x]</m> is the largest integer less than or equal to <m>x</m>.  Prove that, for every positive integer <m>m</m>, the sequence <me>m, f(m), f(f(m)), f(f(f(m))), \dots</me> contains at least one square of an integer.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Assume <m>m = k^2 + j</m> where <m>0 \leq j \leq 2k</m>.</p></hint>
<solution>
<p>(Based on a solution by Steven Oslan)  Let <m>m = k^2 + j</m> where <m>0 \leq j \leq 2k</m>. We consider this the <m>(k,j)</m> position, with an excess of <m>j</m>.  Consider the following three cases depending on the current position.
	<ul>
		<li><p>Case 0: <m>j=0</m>. In this case, we are done! </p></li>
		<li><p>Case 1: <m>1 \leq j \leq k</m>.  <m>f(m)=k^2 + j + k</m>; so <m>f(m)</m> places us in position <m>(k,j+k)</m> which is Case 2 since  <m>k+1 \leq j +k \leq 2k.</m></p></li>
		<li><p>Case 2: <m>k+1 \leq j \leq 2k</m>.   In this case, 
		<m>f(m)=k^2 + j + k = = (k+1)^2 + j-k-1</m>, and <m>0 \leq j-k-1 \leq k-1</m>. This puts us into either Case 0 or Case 1.</p></li>
	</ul>
Notice that applying <m>f</m> successively bounces us between cases 1 and 2 until we are sent into Case 0.  Starting in Case 1 with an excess of <m>j</m>, the excess increases by <m>k</m> in the next application of <m>f</m> but then the following application of <m>f</m> decreases the excess by <m>k+1</m>, so that these two application reduce the excess by 1, to <m>j-1</m>.  Therefore, <m>2 j</m> steps after being in case 1, we are done.
</p>
</solution>
</exercise>

<exercise number="9">
<statement>
<p>Find all integral solutions to <m>\left|p^r-q^s\right|=1</m>, where <m>p</m> and <m>q</m> are primes and <m>r</m> and <m>s</m> are positive
integers greater than or equal to 2. Prove that there are no other solutions than the ones you list.
</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution>
<p>This was A3 in the 1976 Putnam.</p>
</solution>
 -->
 </exercise>

<exercise number="10">
<statement>
<p>What is the sum of the digits of the sum of the digits of the sum of the digits of <m>4444^{4444}</m>?</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
 -->
<solution>
<p>Let <m>S(n)</m> be the sum of the base 10 digits of <m>n</m>.  Since  <m>10^k \equiv 1 \pmod{9}</m> for all <m>k \geq 0</m>, 
<me>s \equiv S(n) \equiv S^{2}(n) \equiv S^{3}(n) \pmod{9}</me>,
we can determine the residue of the desired value mod 9 by identifying the pattern in the powers of <m>4444</m>. 
<me>\begin{split}
4444^1 \equiv 7 \pmod{9}\\
4444^2 \equiv 4 \pmod{9}\\
4444^3 \equiv 1 \pmod{9}\\
4444^4 \equiv 7 \pmod{9}
\end{split}
</me>
The powers are cyclic with period 3, and so <m>S^3(4444^{4444}) \equiv 7 \pmod{9}</m>.</p>
<p>Now we need to do some estimation.  First we bound  <m>S(4444^{4444})</m>.   
<me>4444^{4444} \lt 1000^{5000} = 10^{15000} \Rightarrow S(4444^{4444}) \leq 9\cdot 15000 = 135000</me>
The sum of the digits of <m>S(4444^{4444})</m> is no more than the sum of the digits of 13499, or 35. Therefore the sum of the digits of  <m>S(S(4444^{4444}))</m> is bounded by the sum of digits of integers that are less than or equal to 35.  The maximum is then the sum of digits of 29, or 11.   The bound of 11 on <m>S^3(4444^{4444})</m> combined with the fact that it is congruent to 7 mod 9 implies that our answer is 7.</p>
</solution></exercise>

<exercise number="11">
<statement>
<p>Let <m>n</m> be an integer greater than or equal to four.  Each of the numbers <m>x_1</m>, <m>x_2</m>, ..., <m>x_n</m> equal 1 or -1, and
 <me>\begin{split}
x_1x_2x_3x_4+x_2x_3x_4x_5+x_3x_4x_5x_6+\cdots+x_{n-3}x_{n-2}x_{n-1}x_n+\\
   x_{n-2}x_{n-1}x_nx_1+x_{n-1}x_nx_1x_2+x_nx_1x_2x_3=0
	\end{split}</me>.
Prove that <m>n</m> is divisible by 4.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Use odd/even parity twice.</p></hint>
<solution>
<p>The fact that each term equal <m>\pm 1</m> and they balance to 0 implies that <m>n</m> must be even.  To infer a further factor of 2 in <m>n</m> we note that if the terms in the given sum are multiplied the result is <m>(-1)^{n/2}</m>.   But if we look at this product closely we see that each of the <m>x_i</m>'s appears four times, so the product must be 1.  Therefore <m>n/2</m> is even and we are done.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>

<exercise number="12">
<statement>
<p>Find all positive integers <m>n</m> such that <m>n!</m> ends in exactly 1000 zeros.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Count the factors of 5 in <m>n!</m>.</p></hint>
<solution>
<p>The number of zeros that appear at the end of <m>n!</m> is equal to the total number of factors of 5 in <m>n!</m>.  We also need factors of 2, but there are an excess of those as we increase <m>n</m>.  The number of factors of 5 in <m>n!</m> is 
<me>z(n)=\sum_{k=1}^{\infty} \lfloor \frac{n}{5^k} \rfloor</me>
The first term of this sum is <m>800</m> when <m>n=4000</m> and <m>1000</m> when <m>n=5000</m>, so direct calculation starting at <m>4000</m> would seem to make sense. In fact <m>z(4005)=1000</m> Therefore integers from <m>4005</m> to <m>4009</m> are what we are looking for.  
<!-- 
Some calculation can be avoided if you are aware of a Theorem attributed to Legandre that says that if <m>p</p> is a prime, then the number of factors of <m>p</m> in <m>n!</m> is 
<m>\frac{n−s_{p}(n)}{p−1}</m>, where <m>s_{p}(n)</m> is the sum of the digits in the base <m>p</m> representation of <m>n</m>.  Since <m>1000_{ten}=1300_{five}</m>, <m>s_5(1000)=4</m>.  Therefore we would solve <m>1000=\frac{n-4}{4}</m>.  This gives us 4004	
 -->
</p>
</solution>

</exercise>

<exercise number="13">
<statement>
<p>Prove that among any three distinct integers we can find two, say <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, such that the number <m>a^3b - a b^3</m> is a multiple of 10.</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint> -->
<solution>
<p>No matter which two integers are selected, <m>f(a,b)=a^3b - a b^3=a b (a-b)(a+b)</m> will be even.  If <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> are odd, their sum will be even. Less obvious is whether  <m>f(a,b)</m> will be divisible by 5. Not every pair produces a multiple of 5, such as <m>f(2,1)=6</m>.  If any one of the given integers is a multiple of 5, we are done, so assume we have no multiples of five given.  This means that each of the three integers can be mapped to one of the two sets <m>\{1,4\}</m> or <m>\{2,3\}</m> according to which set its residue mod 5 belongs.   By the pigeonhole principle, there are two integers, <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, that map to the same set.  If their residues are equal, then they differ by a multiple of 5 and if their residues are different, their sum is a multiple of 5.  Either way, <m>f(a,b)</m> be a multiple of 5.</p>
</solution>

</exercise>
<exercise number="14">
<statement>
<p>
	Prove that for any positive integer <m>n</m> there exists an <m>n</m>-digit number divisible by <m>2^n</m> and containing only the digits 2 and 3.
</p>

</statement>
<solution>
<p>(Proof by induction) Let <m>p(n)</m> be the statement that there exists an <m>n</m> digit integer with base 10 representation using only digits 2 and 3 that is divisible by <m>2^n</m>.  The basis, <m>p(1)</m> is clearly true since 2 satisfies the conditions.</p>
<p>Assume <m>p(n)</m> is true for some <m>n \ge 1</m>, and <m>a=2^n b</m> satisfies the conditions in that case.  If <m>b</m> is odd, then <m>3\cdot 10^n + a = 2^n(5^n\cdot 3 + b)</m> prepends <m>a</m> with the digit 3 and is divisible by <m>2^{n+1}</m> since <m>5^n\cdot 3 + b</m> is even.  If <m>b</m> is even, then <m>2\cdot 10^n + a = 2^{n+1}\cdot 5^n + 2^n\cdot b</m> satisfies the desired condition since both terms of the sum are divisible by <m>2^{n+1}</m> and 2 is prepended to <m>a</m>.</p>
<p>A second proof, attributed to Nicholas Raymond, is to note that there are <m>2^n</m> different positive integers with <m>n</m> digits, each 2 or 3.  We can prove that there is a one-to one correspondence between these integers and the residues <m>\mod{2^n}</m>, <m>\{ 0, 1, 2, \dots, 2^{n-1} \}</m>.  This implies that exactly one of these integers is congruent to 0 and so must be divisible by <m>2^n</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise><statement>
<p>(2019 Putnam B-1) Denote by <m>\mathbb{Z}^2</m> the set of all points <m>(x,y)</m> in the plane with integer coordinates. For each integer <m>n \geq 0</m>, let <m>P_n</m> be the subset of <m>\mathbb{Z}^2</m> consisting of the point <m>(0,0)</m> together with all points <m>(x,y)</m> such that <m>x^2 + y^2 = 2^k</m> for some integer <m>k \leq n</m>. Determine, as a function of <m>n</m>, the number of four-point subsets of <m>P_n</m> whose elements are the vertices of a square.</p>
</statement>
<solution>
<p>Note that <m>P_0 = \{ (0,0), (1,0), (-1,0), (0,1), (0,-1)\}</m>.  For <m>n \geq 1</m>, let  <m>P_n' =P_n - P_{n-1}</m>.  First, prove that if <m>n</m> is odd, then <m>P_n' = \{(\pm 2^{(n-1)/2},\pm 2^{(n-1)/2})\}</m>; and if <m>n</m> is even, <m>P_n' = \{(\pm 2^{n/2},0),(0,\pm 2^{n/2})\}</m>..  Both cases can be proven by induction.</p>
<p>Let <m>S(n)</m> be the number of four point subsets of <m>P_n</m> that are the vertices of a square.  Note that <m>S(0)=1</m>.  For <m>n \geq 1</m> notice that by adding <m>P_{n}'</m> to <m>P_{n-1}</m> we get an additional five squares - the square formed by <m>P_{n}'</m>, and the four squares that make up a quarter of that large square. Therefore <m>S(n) = 5 + S(n-1)</m> and so <m>S(n)=5n + 1</m>.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>

<exercise><statement><p>Does there exist a positive integer with the property that the sum of the (base 10) digits of it’s square is equal to 100?  If so, find one. What if 100 is replaced with 2019?</p></statement>
<hint>
<p>Before launching into a search of whether a number  that we seek exists, it is worth considering the problem mod 9 since the sum of the digits of a positive integer is congruent mod 9 to the integer itself.   Controlling the digits of a square is easiest with certain special numbers.   One such type number is <m>10^k-d</m> where <m>k</m> is a positive integer and <m>d</m> is a digit.</p>  
</hint>
<solution><p>Observe that <m>(10^k - 2)^2</m> is an integer whose digits consist of <m>k</m> nines, a single six, some zeros, and then a 4.   Therefore we get the number when <m>k=11</m>.  Following the pattern of digits in <m>11^2</m>, <m>111^2</m>, <m>1111^2, \dots</m> doesn't quite get what we want, but prepending an integer with all ones with a 10 works.   Since <m>2019 \equiv 2 \pmod{9}</m> no square can have sum of digits equal to 2019.</p></solution>
</exercise>


<!-- 
<exercise><statement><p>Let <m>0 \leq k \leq n</m> be integers, <m>n \neq 0</m> and let <m>p</m> be a prime.  Consider the base <m>p</m> representations of <m>n</m> and <m>k</m> with the latter padded with zeros to have the same number of digits as the former:
<me> n = \sum_{i=0}^r n_i p^i \textrm{  and   }k = \sum_{i=0}^r k_i p^i.</me>
with <m>0 \leq k_i,n_i \lt p</m>, <m>n_r \neq 0</m>.
<ol label="(a)">
<li><p>Prove that <m>\binom{n}{k} \equiv \prod_{i=0}^r \binom{n_i}{k_i} \pmod{p}</m>.</p></li>
<li><p>Compute <m>\binom{75}{17} \pmod{11}</m>.</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</statement>
<solution>
<p>Note that <m>(1+x)^n \equiv \prod_{i=0}^{r} (1+x^{p^i})^{n_i} \pmod{p}</m>.  Look at the coefficient of <m>x^k</m> on both sides of this equivalence.</p>
</solution>
</exercise>
 -->
</exercises>
</chapter> 