<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- MBX -->
<chapter xml:id="c-probability">
<title>Probability</title>
<introduction><p>If <m>x</m> is a random variable with outcomes <m>x_1, x_2. x_3, \ldots</m> and corresponding probabilities <m>p_1, p_2, p_3, \ldots</m>, then the expected value of <m>x</m> is <m>x_1p_2+ x_2p_2+ x_3p_3+\ldots</m>.</p>
</introduction>

<!-- 
<section>
<title>Examples</title>
<p>Warm-up: What is the probability that a random five-card poker hand is a flush? a straight? </p>
</section>  
 -->

<section xml:id="s-conditional-probability">
<title>Conditional Probability</title>
<example xml:id="ex-family-matters"><title>Family Matters</title><p>
Assume that the probability that a child is born a boy is exactly <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>.  Now suppose you are told that a certain family has two children and one of them is a boy.  What is probability that the family has two boys?  Our intuition may tell us a certain answer, but many of us are wrong. This is a case for conditional probability.</p></example>
<definition xml:id="def-conditional-probability">
	<title>Conditional Probability</title>
	<idx>Conditional Probability</idx>
	<notation><usage>P(A \mid H)</usage><description>Probability of <m>A</m> given <m>H</m></description></notation>
	<statement><p>Suppose a random event takes place and let <m>H</m> a condition on the event that has a positive probability. The probability that a second condition, <m>A</m>, is met with knowledge that <m>H</m> is true is called the <q>the probability of <m>A</m> conditioned on <m>H</m>,</q> denoted <m>P(A \mid H)</m>.</p></statement>
	</definition>

<theorem>
<title>The Law of Conditional Probability</title>
<statement>
<p>Given a random event with a condition, <m>H</m>, that has a positive probability. Let <m>A</m> be a second condition on this event.  Then 
			<me>P(A \mid H)= \frac{P(A \wedge H)}{P(H)}</me></p>
</statement>
</theorem>

<p>In the example above, the random event of two children being born in sequence has four equally likely outcomes; BB, BG, GB, GG.  We are told that one of the first three has occured, so <m>P(H) =\frac{3}{4}</m> in this case.   The condition that one of the children is boy and both are boys is the same the condition that both are boys, so <m>P(A \wedge H) = \frac{1}{4}</m> in this case, therefore the probability we want is <m>\frac{1/4}{3/4} =\frac{1}{3}</m>.  This conclusion often surprises people.  Did it surprise you?</p>  
</section>  
<!-- Kelly criterion ?-->
<exercises>
<title>Exercises</title>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Steph Kuri shoots free throws on a basketball court. She makes the first and misses the second, and thereafter the probability that she makes the next shot is equal to the proportion of shots she has made so far. What is the probability that she makes exactly 50 of her first 100 shots?</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>King Arthur is sick of fights for inheritance and decides to announce the following law. From now on, no family will be allowed to have another child after a boy is born. What will happen to the percentage of males if the law is followed?</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Four players in a game, N(orth), W(est), S(outh), and E(ast) sit at a round table. N holds a gold coin. One of three things happen, each with probability 1/3: N passes the coin to his right to W, N passes the coin to his left to E, or N walks away with the coin and the game is over. In the first two cases, the holder of the coin repeats the previous step, passing the coin to the right or left, or keeping the coin. What are the probabilities of winning for the four players?</p>
</statement>
<solution>
<p>We will abbreviate the probability that player <m>X</m> wins to <m>P(X)</m>.  By the symmetry of the game, <m>P(W)=P(E)</m>.  Also, we observe that 
	<me>\begin{split}
	P(W)&amp;=P(W | \text{ the coin passes to }W)/3 + P(W |\text{ the coin passes to }E)/3\\
		&amp;=P(N)/3 + P(S)/3\\
		\end{split}
	</me>
and 
	<me>\begin{split}
	P(S)&amp;=P(S | \text{ the coin passes to }W)/3 + P(S |\text{ the coin passes to }E)/3\\
		&amp;=P(W)/3 + P(E)/3 = \frac{2}{3} P(W)\\
		\end{split}
	</me>
Finally, since someone must win eventually, <m>P(N)+P(W)+P(S)+P(E)=1</m>.  The four equations we have listed have the single solution <m>P(N)=\frac{7}{15}</m>, <m>P(W)=P(E)=\frac{1}{5}</m>, and <m>P(S)=\frac{2}{15}</m></p>
<p>There are two other ways to reach the same solution to this problem.  One is to use the fact this is Markov Chain.  The game has eight states, four are for the situations where the coin has still not been won but is held one of the players.  The other four states are called absorbing states and represent the outcomes where each player can win.  In this context, we want to compute the probabilities of landing each of the absorbing states.  There are matrix techniques for computing these probabilities.  See Kemeny and Snell <xref ref="biblio-kemeny"/> for details. Another approach is to model the game with a <term>stochastic abacus</term>.  We recommend the reader to Propp <xref ref="biblio-propp"/> or Torrence <xref ref="biblio-torrence"/>  for information on this approach.</p></solution>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement><p>Suppose two teams play a series of games in which the probability that either wins any of the games is <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>.  If they play a best
of seven series, where the winner is the first to win four games, what is the probability that the series lasts seven games?</p></statement>
<answer><p><m>\frac{5}{16}</m></p></answer>
<solution><p>
In order for the series to go seven games, the teams must split the first six games. Imagine that they play out six games no matter what happens.  There are <m>2^6</m> equally likely outcomes and in <m>\binom{6}{3}=20</m> of the cases the teams split. Therefore, the probability of a seven games
series <m>\frac{20}{2^6}= \frac{5}{16}</m>.</p></solution>
</exercise>

<exercise><title>Simplified NCAA basketball pool</title>
<statement>
<p>There are 64 teams who play single elimination tournament, hence 6 rounds, and you have to predict all the winners in
all 63 games. Your score is then computed as follows: 32 points for correctly predicting the final winner, 16 points for each correct finalist, and so on, down to 1 point for every correctly predicted winner for the first round. Knowing nothing about any team, you flip fair coins to decide every one of your 63 bets. Compute your expected number of points.</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Three real numbers <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, <m>c</m> are randomly (and uniformly) chosen from the interval <m>[0, 1]</m>. What is the probability that there exists a triangle with sides <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, <m>c</m>?</p>
</statement>
<solution><p>Given any <m>c</m> between 0 and 1, we can determine the probablity that <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> combine with <m>c</m> to form a triangle by measuring the area of the region indicated by the inequalities in <xref ref="fig-prob-of-triangle"/>. That probability is <m>\frac{(4-3c)c}{2}</m>. We can then integrate this probability over the interval <m>[0,1]</m> to get a probability for the three random numbers of <m>\frac{1}{2}</m></p>
         <figure xml:id="fig-prob-of-triangle">
                <caption>Region of triangle formation
                </caption>
                <image source="images/prob-of-triangle.png">
                    <description>For a given  <m>c</m> the region in the <m>a b</m>-plane in which a triangle is formed.</description>
                </image>
            </figure>

</solution>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Let <m>p_n</m> be the probability that <m>c + d</m> is a perfect square, where the integers <m>c</m> and <m>d</m> are selected independently at random from the set <m>\{1, . . . , n\}</m>. Find <m>\lim_{n\to \infty } \, \sqrt{n} p_n</m>.</p>
</statement>
<hint><p>Start by counting points in the diagonals of the square array of lattice points <m>(c,d)</m> such that <m>c+d</m> is a square.  There are two formulae for the number of points: one for diagonals that produce the squares of the numbers 2 through <m>\lfloor \sqrt{n+1} \rfloor</m>, and a second for those that produce squares of the the numbers from <m>\lfloor \sqrt{n+1} \rfloor +1</m> to <m>\lfloor \sqrt{2n} \rfloor</m>.</p></hint>
<!-- 
<solution><p>This was a 1982 Putnam problem.</p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>
<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Two real numbers <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> are chosen at random in the interval <m>(0,1)</m> with respect to the uniform distribution. What is the probability that
the closest integer to <m>x/y</m> is even? Express the answer in the form <m>r + s \pi</m>, where <m>r</m> and <m>s</m> are rational numbers.</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Let <m>\alpha  \in  [0,1]</m> be an arbitrary number, rational or irrational. The only randomizing device is an unfair coin, with probability <m>p \in (0,1)</m> of heads. Design a game between Alice and Bob so that Alice's winning probability is exactly <m>\alpha</m>. The game has to end in a finite number of tosses with probability 1.</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Begin with the set <m>\{1,2,\dots,n\}</m>. Toss a coin <m>n</m> times, once for each member of the set. Keep the elements that scored <q>Heads</q> and discard the elements that got <q>Tails</q>. You now have a certain subset <m>S</m> of the original set. Call this whole process a <q>step</q>. Now take a step from <m>S</m>. That is, toss a coin for each element of <m>S</m>, and keep those that get <q>Heads</q>, getting a sub-subset <m>S'</m>, etc. This game halts when the empty set is reached. Let <m>f(n,k,r)</m> be the probability that after <m>k</m> steps, exactly <m>r</m> objects remain.
<ol label="(a)">
<li><p>Find a recurrence relation for <m>f</m>, find the generating function for <m>f</m>, and find <m>f</m> itself. </p></li>
<li><p>What is the average number of steps in a complete game?</p></li>
</ol>
</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
<solution><p></p></solution>
 -->
</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>An urn contains a number of colored balls, with the same number of balls in each color. If 20 balls of a new color are added to the urn, the probability of drawing (without replacement) two balls of the same color is not changed. How many balls are in the urn (before the new balls are added)?</p>
</statement>
<solution><p>Let <m>c</m> be the number of colors represented in the urn and <m>n</m> the number of balls of each color.  The condition we want to satisfy is <m>\frac{c (n-1) n+380}{(c n+19)
   (c n+20)}=\frac{n-1}{c n-1}</m>.  Manipulating this equation, we get <m>\frac{n (c (2 n-21)+19)}{(c
   n-1) (c n+19) (c n+20)}=0</m>, which implies that <m>c(2 n-21)+19=0</m>.  The only pair integer pairs <m>(c,n)</m> to this equation are <m>(1,1)</m> and <m>(19,10)</m>.  The first must be rejected, and so the only solution is that there are initially 10 balls of each of 19 colors. Adding 20 of a new color will not change the probability of matching colors.  In either case the probability will be <m>\frac{1}{19}</m>. This is the only solution.</p>
</solution>

</exercise>

<exercise>
<statement>
<p>Suppose that the probability that the length of a telephone call is between <m>t_1</m> and <m>t_2</m> minutes,  <m>t_1 \lt t_2</m> is <m>\int_{t_1}^{t_2} e^{-t} \, dt</m>.   What is the probability that a phone call lasts less than one minute.  What is the probability that a phone call lasts less than two minutes given that it lasts at least one minute?</p>
</statement>
<!-- 
<hint><p></p></hint>
 -->
<solution><p>Let <m>X</m> be a random variable that is the length of a phone call. The probability that a call lasts no more than one minute is <m>Pr(X \lt 1) = \int_{0}^{1} \, e^{-t} dt = \frac{e-1}{e}</m>.  The probability that it lasts less than two minutes given that it last at least one minute is 
<me>Pr(X \lt 2 | X \geq 1)= \frac{Pr(1 \leq X \lt 2)}{Pr(X \geq 1)} = \frac{\frac{e-1}{e^2}}{\frac{1}{e}}=\frac{e-1}{e}</me> 
The property that these two probabilities are equal is called  memorylessness.  </p></solution>
</exercise>

</exercises>
</chapter> 









 




