<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<references><idx><h>References</h></idx>
<introduction>
<p>Many of the problems in this book have been used in multiple sources.  If  a problem was set in a know competition, it cited in the problem statement.   For most other problems, no effort has been made to identify when it was first posed, but most of the problems in this book among the following list of sources.  An additional source of problems are the problem sections of the Mathematical Association of America journals:
<ul>
<li><p>The American Mathematical Monthley</p></li>
<li><p>Mathematics Magazine</p></li>
<li><p>The College Mathematics Journal</p></li>
</ul>
For problems that were posed in these journals, the source is cited with the problems.</p>
</introduction>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-putnam-2">Alexanderson, Klosinski and Larson, <title>The William Lowell Putnam mathematical competition. Problems and solutions: 1965-1984</title>, MAA, 19__</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-appel-1976">Appel, K., and W. Haken, <title>Every Planar Map Is 4-colorable</title>,  Bull, Am. Math. Soc. 82 (1976): 711-12.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="doerr-2019">Doerr, A, and K. Levasseur, <title>Applied Discrete Structures</title></biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-allenby-1983">Erickson, Martin J., Flowers, Joe <title>Principles of Mathematical Problem Solving</title>, Prentice Hall, 1999.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-putnam-1">Gleason, Greenwood and Kelly, <title>The William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition. Problems and solutions: 1938-1964</title>, MAA, 19__</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-havil-2003">Havil, Julian <title>Gamma, Exploring Euler's Constant</title>, Princeton U Press, 2003.</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-putnam-3">Kedlaya, Poonen and Vakil, <title>The William Lowell Putnam Mathematical Competition 1985-2000: Problems, Solutions and Commentary</title>, MAA, 20__</biblio>
<biblio type="raw" xml:id="biblio-klamkin-1986">Klamkin, M. S.<title>International Mathematical Olympiads 1978-1985 and Forty Supplementary Problems</title>, Mathematical Association of America, 1986.</biblio>
</references>